<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text Diplomacy -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CRUSADER</Tag>
		<English>Crusader</English>
		<French>Croisé</French>
		<German>Kreuzfahrer</German>
		<Italian>Crociato</Italian>
		<Spanish>Cruzado</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CRUSADER_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Crusader unit is especially suitable for taking cities.</English>
		<French>Le Croisé est particulièrement approprié à prendre des villes.</French>
		<German>Der Kreuzfahrer ist besonders verwendbar für das Nehmen der Städte.</German>
		<Italian>Il Crociato è particolarmente adatto a prendere le città.</Italian>
		<Spanish>El Cruzado es especialmente conveniente para tomar ciudades.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CRUSADER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Crusades were a series of religion-driven military campaigns waged by much of Christian Europe against external and internal opponents. Crusades were fought mainly against Muslims, though campaigns were also directed against pagan Slavs, Jews, Russian and Greek Orthodox Christians, Mongols, Cathars, Hussites, Waldensians, Old Prussians and political enemies of the popes. Crusaders took vows and were granted an indulgence for past sins. The Crusades were a series of religion-driven military campaigns waged by much of Christian Europe against external and internal opponents. Crusades were fought mainly against Muslims, though campaigns were also directed against pagan Slavs, Jews, Russian and Greek Orthodox Christians, Mongols, Cathars, Hussites, Waldensians, Old Prussians and political enemies of the popes. Crusaders took vows and were granted an indulgence for past sins. The Crusades originally had the goal of recapturing Jerusalem and the Holy Land from Muslim rule and were launched in response to a call from the Eastern Orthodox Byzantine Empire for help against the expansion of the Muslim Seljuk Turks into Anatolia. The term is also used to describe contemporaneous and subsequent campaigns conducted through to the 16th century in territories outside the Levant usually against pagans, heretics, and peoples under the ban of excommunication for a mixture of religious, economic, and political reasons. Rivalries among both Christian and Muslim powers led also to alliances between religious factions against their opponents, such as the Christian alliance with the Sultanate of Rum during the Fifth Crusade. The Crusades had far-reaching political, economic, and social impacts, some of which have lasted into contemporary times. Because of internal conflicts among Christian kingdoms and political powers, some of the crusade expeditions were diverted from their original aim, such as the Fourth Crusade, which resulted in the sack of Christian Constantinople and the partition of the Byzantine Empire between Venice and the Crusaders. The Sixth Crusade was the first crusade to set sail without the official blessing of the Pope. The Seventh, Eighth and Ninth Crusades resulted in Mamluk and Hafsid victories, as the Ninth Crusade marked the end of the Crusades in the Middle East.</English>
		<French>Les croisades du Moyen Âge sont des pèlerinages armés prêchés par le pape. La vision traditionnelle identifie l'époque des croisades à la période 1095-1291, du concile de Clermont à la prise de Saint-Jean-d'Acre, et se limite aux expéditions qui ont eu la Terre Sainte pour objectif et l'Orient pour théâtre d'opérations. Dans la définition large, toutes les guerres contre les Infidèles et les hérétiques, sanctionnées par le Pape qui y attache des récompenses spirituelles et des indulgences, sont des croisades. La Reconquista, croisade d'Espagne, en fait ainsi partie. Les dates sont alors beaucoup plus larges et mènent jusqu'à la bataille de Lépante (1571) dans la seconde moitié du XVIe siècle. C'est la définition dite traditionnelle qui est retenue pour cet article. La première croisade débute en 1095, soit vingt-quatre ans après la bataille de Manzikert et dix-sept ans après l'invasion turque. Contre toute attente et toute prévision, elle se marque par une forte participation populaire, c'est-à-dire constituée de milliers de pèlerins piétons. Elle est aussi l'occasion pour le pape d'occuper la noblesse dans sa lutte de pouvoir avec elle. Elle aboutit à la fondation d'États latins (ou francs) en Orient. La défense de ces États est à l'origine de l'organisation des sept autres croisades principales ; de 1095 à 1291 (date de la perte des dernières positions latines en Orient), de nombreux groupes de soldats et de pèlerins ont participé à l'aventure des croisades. À partir de la quatrième croisade qui aboutit à la prise de Constantinople en 1204, l'idée de croisade est dévoyée, et des expéditions sont organisées par le pape contre ses opposants chrétiens (Albigeois, Hohenstaufen, Aragon, Hussites ...) ou païens (baltes). Si elles permettent le maintien des États latins d'Orient, elles n'ont plus pour objectif Jérusalem et sont l'occasion pour la papauté de lever des impôts sur le clergé. De fait, seules l'Église catholique et les cités marchandes italiennes ont bénéficié des croisades.</French>
		<German>Die Kreuzzüge der christlichen Völker des Abendlands waren strategisch, religiös und wirtschaftlich motivierte Kriege. Im engeren Sinne werden unter den Kreuzzügen nur die Orientkreuzzüge verstanden, die sich gegen die muslimischen Staaten im Nahen Osten richteten. Im einem erweiterten Sinne werden auch die Feldzüge gegen nicht christianisierte Völker wie Wenden, Finnen und Balten, gegen Ketzer wie die Albighenser und gegen die Ostkirche dazu gezählt. Dem Ersten Kreuzzug war ein Hilferuf des byzantinischen Kaisers Alexios I. Komnenos um militärische Unterstützung gegen die Seldschuken vorausgegangen. Dies löste den Aufruf Papst Urbans II. 1095 in Clermont aus, der zur Befreiung Jerusalems und des "Heiligen Landes' aus der Hand der Muslime aufforderte, mehr als acht Jahrzehnte, nachdem es in der Regierungszeit des fatimidischen Kalifen al-Hakim 1009 zur Zerstörung der Grabeskirche gekommen war, eines der größten Heiligtümer des Christentums. Nachdem ein Kreuzfahrerheer 1099 Jerusalem erobert hatte, wurden in Outremer insgesamt vier Kreuzfahrerstaaten gegründet. Infolge ihrer Bedrohung durch die muslimischen Anrainerstaaten wurden weitere Kreuzzüge durchgeführt, denen meistens kaum ein Erfolg beschieden war. Das Königreich Jerusalem erlitt 1187 in der Schlacht bei Hattin eine schwere Niederlage, auch Jerusalem ging wieder verloren. Mit Akkon fiel 1291 die letzte Kreuzfahrerfestung in Outremer. Nach dem Ersten Kreuzzug wurde der Begriff "Kreuzzug" auch auf andere militärische Aktionen ausgeweitet, deren Ziel nicht das Heilige Land war.</German>
		<Italian>Le crociate furono una serie di spedizioni militari, avvenute tra l'XI e il XIII secolo, che furono benedette dal Papato per motivi eminentemente religiosi ma che ebbero anche non trascurabili moventi politico-economici all'interno del mondo feudale medievale europeo e bizantino.Sono altresì considerate da alcuni come la risposta della Cristianità al jihad islamico del VII secolo ed ebbero come scopo la difesa dei Cristiani in Terra Santa contro i musulmani. La prima crociata fu quella che ottenne i maggiori successi e portò alla nascita degli stati crociati d'Outremer che sopravvissero fino al 1303. Alla prima crociata seguirono altre spedizioni (circa 8) nel corso del XII e XIII secolo che però quasi mai raggiunsero gli obiettivi che si erano prefissate. Molte anzi degenerarono in violenze insensate e la quarta addirittura vide come conseguenza la presa di Costantinopoli proprio a scapito dei bizantini. In senso più ampio, il termine "crociata" può essere usato negativamente per indicare una qualsiasi guerra dichiarata per motivi religiosi (guerra santa, "crociata contro l'aborto"), ma può significativamente conservare un'accezione semantica positiva quando viene usato per raccomandare alcune campagne d'impronta fortemente ideologica o sociale (ad esempio, "crociata contro il fumo", contro le droghe o contro l'alcol).</Italian>
		<Spanish>Las cruzadas fueron una serie de campañas militares comúnmente hechas a petición del Papado, y que tuvieron lugar entre los siglos XI y XIII, contra los turcos selyúcidas y sarracenos (llamados así los musulmanes) para la reconquista de Tierra Santa. Básicamente, parece que fueron motivadas por los intereses expansionistas de la nobleza feudal, el control del comercio con Asia y el afán hegemónico del papado sobre las monarquías y las iglesias de Oriente, aunque se declararan con principio y objeto de recuperar Tierra Santa para los peregrinos, de los cuales los turcos seléucidas, una vez conquistada Jerusalén, abusaban sin piedad. Posiblemente, las motivaciones de quienes participaban en ellas fueron muy diversas, aunque en muchos casos se puede suponer también un verdadero fervor religioso. Las Cruzadas fueron expediciones emprendidas en cumplimiento de un solemne voto para liberar los Lugares Santos de la dominación musulmana. El origen de la palabra se remonta a la cruz hecha de tela y usada como insignia en la ropa exterior de los que tomaron parte en esas iniciativas.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>